Guide to the Amanda Smith Papers, 1950s-2000s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Amanda Smith papers 1950s-2000s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Amanda J. Mackay.
16.0 linear feet Extent: 12000 Items
Author (fiction and non-fiction) and gender equity consultant from Durham, N.C. Collection includes materials from Smith's literary career as an author of mystery novels, files from her work as a gender equity consultant, her newspaper columns on gender in the workplace, and materials from her work with youth at St. Philip's Episcopal Church in Durham. Also includes a small amount of correspondence from Smith's college years and family photographs from the early 20th century. The files relating to her fiction writing also include a set of audiocassettes related to one of her books. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.01219
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Amanda Smith Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Biographical Note
Amanda J. Mackay Smith is an author and gender equity consultant from Durham, N.C. Her published works include mystery novels (under the name Amanda Mackay) with Duke and Durham themes. Smith is also responsible for feminist work in the Episcopal church, especially for developing curricula around sexuality for children, teens, and adults. She also developed secular educational materials around gender and sexuality and taught workshops (within and outside of the Church) and in a vocational education school. In addition, she is a journalist, having written a syndicated column from 1989-1991 called "The Sexes: Working Together," and did pioneering work with individual legislators and government offices such as the State Dept. of Occupational Education. In the late 1970s, Smith was honored at the White House as one of the two founding mothers of gender equity in Vocational Education.
Collection Overview
Collection includes materials from Smith's literary career as an author of mystery novels, files from her work as a gender equity consultant, her newspaper columns on gender in the workplace, and materials from her work with youth at St. Philip's Episcopal Church in Durham. Also includes a small amount of correspondence from Smith's college years and family photographs from the early 20th century. The files relating to her fiction writing also include a set of audiocassettes related to one of her books. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Smith, Amanda J. Mackay; Novelists, American; Detective and mystery stories, American -- Authors; Sex discrimination -- Education; Discrimination in employment -- United States; Equal pay for equal work -- United States; Job evaluation; Educational equalization -- United States; Sex discrimination in education -- United States; Sexism -- United States; Youth -- Religious life; Faith development; Italy -- Description and travel; Audiocassettes; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Accession 2011-1034, (12 boxes)
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Literary Agents mailings, May 1997 (Box 1)
  - Files from work as a gender equity consultant (Box 1)
  - Sexual harassment/assault resource files (Box 1)
  - St. Philip's Episcopal Church materials
    - Journey to Adulthood (J2A) files, 1990s-2000s, including trip to Italy, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Parish Partnership Training files (Box 1)
    - Journey to Adulthood binder (Box 2)
    - Episcopal Diocese of NC: Sexual Ethics Training binder (Box 2)
  - Handouts and other training material for gender equity (Box 2)
  - Workshops and organization visits (Box 2)
  - Subject Files
    - Abortion to Children (Box 2)
    - Clergy/Women-Pornography (Box 3)
    - Pregnancy, Teen-Zines (Box 4)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Sex Equity in Apprenticeships (Box 4)
  - New Pioneers: A Project to Eliminate Sex Bias in Occupational Education, by Amanda Smith, 1978 (Box 5)
  - New Pioneers: A Program to Expand Sex Role Expectations in Elementary and Secondary Education, by Amanda Smith, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks (Box 5)
  - Measures of Educational Equity for Women: A Research Monograph (Box 5)
  - "The Academic and Professional Alliance for a Responsible Congress," M.A. Thesis (Box 5)
  - Speaking in Strings DVD (Box 5)
  - Travel lectures, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and postcards, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Programs and cards, 1950s-1960s (Box 5)
  - Wedding programs, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Old family photographs and snapshots (Box 6)
  - Italy travel materials (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 6)
  - New Pioneers program work at the NC Dept. of Public Instruction (Box 6)
  - NC Dept. of Occupational Education work (Box 6)
  - Training conferences, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Workshop handouts used by Smith in her gender equity consulting (Box 7)
  - "The Sexes: Working Together" weekly newspaper columns, May 1989-January 1992 (incomplete) (Box 8)
  - "The Sexes: Working Together" weekly newspaper columns, Sept. 1992-Aug. 1993 (Box 8)
  - Newspaper column files (Box 9)
  - Training handouts, including Smith's photographs and biography (Box 9)
  - Writing files
    - Mystery novels, including research files and reviews, 1970s (Box 9)
    - Sex equity writings and correspondence with publishers, 1980s (Box 9)
  - Clippings (Box 10)
  - "Working Together Curriculum Project," Bakersfield Community College curriculum development (Box 10)
  - Smile and Be a Villain drafts (published as Death is Academic) (Box 10)
  - Smile and Be a Villain edited draft (Box 10)
  - Notes and drafts for mystery #4 (Box 10)
  - The Eleventh Hour: The Academic and Professional Alliance for a Responsible Congress, edited by Smith (Box 10)
  - Draft of Partners (non-fiction book on men and women working together) (Box 11)
  - Gender consulting materials (Box 11)
  - Audiotapes for mystery #4 (Box 12)